Guide to the Alan Mara Bateman Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Alan Mara Bateman papers
1907-1968
MS 641
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
8
(8 boxes)
Correspondence, field reports, memoranda, and government documents chiefly relating to Bateman's service on various government commissions, among them the Metals and Minerals Division of the Foreign Economic Administration (1942-1946), the U.S. Missions to Mexico (1942), the President's Materials Policy Commission (1951-1953). The few items from his teaching career at Yale include gradebooks for the years 1907-1955 and reports on the Sheffield Scientific School.
Bateman, Alan M. (Alan Mara), 1889-1971
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of the Yale Geology Department, 1960; Mrs. H. C. Carlisle, 1968; and Mrs. A. Bateman, 1972.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Arrangement
Arranged in two series: I. Correspondence. II. Topical files.
Biographical / Historical
Alan M. Bateman: geologist; field geologist for Harvard University, 1913-1915; taught geology at Harvard, 1916-1925; taught at Yale University, 1925-1941, and chairman of the Geology Department; consultant to industry and government, 1941-1942; director of Metals and Minerals, Foreign Economic Administration, 1942-1946; consultant, 1946-; editor of several journals.
Scope and Contents
Correspondence, field reports, memoranda, and government documents chiefly relating to Bateman's service on various government commissions, among them the Metals and Minerals Division of the Foreign Economic Administration (1942-1946), the U.S. Missions to Mexico (1942), the President's Materials Policy Commission (1951-1953). The few items from his teaching career at Yale include gradebooks for the years 1907-1955 and reports on the Sheffield Scientific School.
Mines and mineral resources; Science; World War, 1939-1945; New Haven (Conn.); Educators; Geologists; Bateman, Alan M. (Alan Mara), 1889-1971; United States. Foreign Economic Administration; United States. President's Materials Policy Commission; Yale University -- Faculty; Yale University. Department of Geology and Geophysics; Yale University. Sheffield Scientific School
- Correspondence, Series I
  - A (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Advisory Committee in Science, Faculty of Arts and Sciences, 1956-1957 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - American Metal Company, 1932-1942 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - American Smelt and Refining Company, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Air pictures: Flint, 1933, 1957 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - B (Box 1, Folder 6-8)
  - Barry, John G., 1942 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Beryllium Committee and report, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Bosch Collection, 1952-1966 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Bridgman, G. Temple, 1942 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Building, 1948-1956 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - C (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Chase, P. W., 1940, 1942, undated (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Civil defense, 1954-1969 (Box 1, Folder 16-20)
  - D (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Defense Materials Procurement Agency, 1951-1953 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Defense Mobilization, Office of, 1953, 1954 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - E (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Emmons Memorial Fellowship, 1948-1960 (Box 2, Folder 25-26)
  - Engineers Joint Council, 1950 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - F (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Ford Foundation, 1954 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Funk and Wagnalls, 1957 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - G (Box 2, Folder 31-33)
  - Geochemical Laboratory, 1959-1960 (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Geochemistry, 1956 (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - Geological Society of America, 1965 (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - Government officials (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - Graduate Club, 1957 (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - Graduate School, 1954-1958, undated (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - H (Box 3, Folder 40-43)
  - Donnel Forster Hewitt Fund, 1948-1958 (Box 3, Folder 44)
  - Higgins Trust Fund, 1950-1958, undated (Box 3, Folder 45)
  - I (Box 3, Folder 46)
  - India Science Congress, 1952-1956 (Box 3, Folder 47-49)
  - Indian letters: Applications, 1952-1959 (Box 3, Folder 50-52)
  - International Affairs, 1946 (Box 3, Folder 53)
  - 18th-22nd International Geological Congresses, 1947-1962, undated (Box 3, Folder 54-57)
  - International Nickel Company Scholarship, 1956, 1957, undated (Box 4, Folder 58)
  - Interviews and recommendations, 1958-1960 (Box 4, Folder 59)
  - J (Box 4, Folder 60)
  - Jackling Fund Committee, 1959-1961 (Box 4, Folder 61-62)
  - Japan - U.S. Government, 1945-1951, undated (Box 4, Folder 63-65)
  - Japanese letters, 1954, 1955, 1959 (Box 4, Folder 66)
  - Jensen, Mead Leroy, 1962 (Box 4, Folder 67)
  - Joint Research and Development Board, 1946, 1947, undated (Box 4, Folder 68)
  - K (Box 4, Folder 69)
  - Latin America (Box 4, Folder 70)
  - Lindgren volume, 1962, 1963 (Box 4, Folder 71)
  - John Lindsley Fund, 1952, 1956, 1957 (Box 4, Folder 72)
  - M (Box 4, Folder 73)
  - Mc (Box 5, Folder 74)
  - Macalder-Kenya, 1937-1942, undated (Box 5, Folder 75)
  - Marler file, 1955 (Box 5, Folder 76)
  - Mersick, C. S., 1968, 1969 (Box 5, Folder 77-78)
  - Messersmith letters, 1942, 1943 (Box 5, Folder 79)
  - Metals and Minerals Division, F.E.A., Undated (Box 5, Folder 80)
  - Metals Reserve Company, 1941, 1942 (Box 5, Folder 81)
  - Mexican Project, 1942 (Box 5, Folder 82)
  - Mexico Treaty papers, 1942, undated (Box 5, Folder 83)
  - MICO Instrument Company, 1940, 1941 (Box 5, Folder 84)
  - Minerology applications, 1939, 1940 (Box 5, Folder 85)
  - Monsanto Chemical Company, 1948, 1949, undated (Box 5, Folder 86)
  - N (Box 5, Folder 87)
  - National Register of Scientific and Technical Personnel, 1954 (Box 5, Folder 88)
  - National Science Foundation, 1957-1961, undated (Box 5, Folder 89)
  - Natural Sciences, Committee on, 1956 (Box 5, Folder 90)
  - O (Box 5, Folder 91)
  - Oral history, 1959 (Box 6, Folder 92)
  - Overbeck, R. M., 1915, 1916 (Box 6, Folder 93)
  - P (Box 6, Folder 94)
  - Pan-American Institute of Mining, Engineering, and Geology, 1945-1949 (Box 6, Folder 95)
  - Physical Sciences and Mathematics, 1946-1956, undated (Box 6, Folder 96)
  - Portuguese Geologic Survey, 1950-1952, undated (Box 6, Folder 97)
  - Positions desired: References, suggestions (A-Z) (Box 6, Folder 98-99)
  - Positions "open" (A-Z)
    - American universities (Box 6, Folder 100)
    - Foreign universities and businesses (Box 6, Folder 101)
  - President's Materials Policy Commission, 1951, 1952, undated (Box 6, Folder 102)
  - Princeton symposium (Box 6, Folder 103)
  - Printing orders, 1947-1954 (Box 6, Folder 104)
  - Q (Box 6, Folder 105)
  - Ra-Re (Box 6, Folder 106)
  - Ri-Ry (Box 7, Folder 107)
  - Rhodesian Selection Trust
    - Chambishi Mine, 1930 (Box 7, Folder 108)
    - Luanshya, 1929-1932 (Box 7, Folder 109)
    - Nikana Concession, 1929-1933 (Box 7, Folder 110)
    - Titcomb, H. A., 1929 (Box 7, Folder 111)
  - Rhodesian Selection Trust and Roan Antelope Copper Mines, 1929-1931 (Box 7, Folder 112)
  - S (Box 7, Folder 113)
  - São Paulo, 1957, 1958 (Box 7, Folder 114)
  - Selective Treatment Company, 1925-1931 (Box 7, Folder 115)
  - Sheffield Scientific School
    - Board of Permanent Officers and Jubilee volume, 1953-1957 (Box 7, Folder 116)
    - Board of Trustees
      - General, 1964-1971 (Box 7, Folder 117-119)
      - Brush Collection of Minerals, 1904-1970 (Box 7, Folder 120)
      - Budget, 1956-1962 (Box 7, Folder 121-124)
      - Budget, 1962-1964 (Box 8, Folder 123-124)
    - Centennial, 1946, 1947, undated (Box 8, Folder 125)
  - Henry Dewitt Smith Fellowship, 1963 (Box 8, Folder 126)
  - Society of Economic Geologists, 1952, 1953 (Box 8, Folder 127)
  - Source Research Council, Inc., 1928, 1929 (Box 8, Folder 128)
  - Survey: Teaching of Sciences, 1953, 1955 (Box 8, Folder 129)
  - T (Box 8, Folder 130)
  - Torch Honor Society, 1935-1962, undated (Box 8, Folder 131)
  - U (Box 8, Folder 132)
  - United Nations Conference on the Conservation and Utilization of Resources, 1949 (Box 8, Folder 133)
  - U.S. Atomic Energy Commission, 1948, 1952 (Box 8, Folder 134)
  - U.S. Government
    - Bills and reports: Bush report, 1946 (Box 8, Folder 135)
    - Economic Cooperation Administration, 1950, 1951 (Box 8, Folder 136)
    - National Minerals Advisory Council, 1945-1951, undated (Box 8, Folder 137)
    - National Security Resources Board, 1949-1953 (Box 8, Folder 138)
  - U.S. Minerals Program, 1948-1951, undated (Box 9, Folder 139)
  - University Council, 1955, undated (Box 9, Folder 140)
  - Urguhart, 1933-1947, undated (Box 9, Folder 141)
  - V (Box 9, Folder 142)
  - Venezuelan trip, 1940 (Box 9, Folder 143)
  - Wa-Wd (Box 9, Folder 144)
  - We-Wg (Box 9, Folder 145)
  - Wh (Box 9, Folder 146)
  - Wi-Wn (Box 9, Folder 147)
  - Wo-Wy (Box 9, Folder 148)
  - Y (Box 9, Folder 149)
  - Yale Fundraising Department, 1952, 1953, undated (Box 9, Folder 150)
  - Yale Graduate School Association, 1966-1969 (Box 9, Folder 151)
  - Yale Scientific Magazine, 1935-1956, undated (Box 9, Folder 152)
  - Yale: Silliman College, 1945-1967, undated (Box 10, Folder 153)
  - Z, 1932, 1934, 1942 (Box 10, Folder 154)
- Topical Files, Series II
  - Bateman-Suarez Agreement: Drafts, 1942, undated (Box 11, Folder 155)
  - Biographical material and articles for Yale publications, 1938-1965 (Box 11, Folder 156)
  - Chilean, Peruvian, Mexican Agreements: Drafts and personal notes from staff meetings, 1942-1945 (Box 11, Folder 157)
  - Civil Defense
    - Booklets, 1965, 1967, 1968 (Box 11, Folder 158)
    - Bulletin, 1958 (Box 11, Folder 159)
    - Policy Board meeting, 1969 (Box 11, Folder 160)
    - Reports, 1953-1970 (Box 11, Folder 161-163)
    - Staff news, 1954-1963 (Box 11, Folder 164)
  - Combined raw materials, 1944, 1945 (Box 11, Folder 165)
  - Commodity reports
    - Aluminum bauxite, 1943 (Box 12, Folder 166)
    - Antinomy, 1942-1944, undated (Box 12, Folder 167)
    - Beryl, 1944, 1953, undated (Box 12, Folder 168)
    - Bismuth and cadmium, 1942-1945, undated (Box 12, Folder 169)
    - Chemicals and fertilizers, 1942-1945 (Box 12, Folder 170)
    - Chrome, 1942-1945, undated (Box 12, Folder 171)
    - Cobalt and Molybdenum, 1942-1944, undated (Box 12, Folder 172)
    - Copper
      - General, 1942-1945, undated (Box 12, Folder 173)
      - Current data, 1943-1945, undated (Box 12, Folder 174)
      - Postwar planning, Undated (Box 12, Folder 175)
      - Projects committees, 1943-1945, undated (Box 12, Folder 176)
    - Iron, Ilmenite, Rutile, Titanium, Pyrite and Zircon, 1942-1944, undated (Box 12, Folder 177)
    - Lead, 1942-1945, undated (Box 12, Folder 178)
    - Lead and Zinc, 1942-1945, undated (Box 13, Folder 179)
    - Manganese, 1942-1945, undated (Box 13, Folder 180)
    - Mercury, 1942-1944, undated (Box 13, Folder 181)
    - Mica, 1942-1945 (Box 13, Folder 182)
    - Nickel, 1943-1952, undated (Box 13, Folder 183)
    - Quartz, 1942-1944, undated (Box 13, Folder 184)
    - Rare metals, 1942-1945, undated (Box 13, Folder 185)
    - Silver, 1944-1945, undated (Box 13, Folder 186)
    - Tantalite, 1942-1945, undated (Box 13, Folder 187)
    - Tin, 1940-1945, undated (Box 13, Folder 188-189)
    - Tungsten, 1942-1945 (Box 13, Folder 190)
    - Vanadium, 1942-1945, undated (Box 14, Folder 191)
    - Zinc, 1942-1944 (Box 14, Folder 192)
    - Summaries: Asbestos, Copper, Iceland Spar, Indian Kyanite, Lead, Nickel, Quartz, 1945, undated (Box 14, Folder 193)
  - Corporations, Miscellaneous: Pyron, Ventures, Snow White, Aldermac, 1942-1944, undated (Box 14, Folder 194)
  - Dewey Decimal Classification, 1936, undated (Box 14, Folder 195)
  - Economic Geology Library: Subject index, 1927 (Box 14, Folder 196)
  - Field reports
    - Africa, 1944, 1945, 1952 (Box 14, Folder 197)
    - Asia (including U.S.S.R.), 1944, 1945, undated (Box 14, Folder 198)
    - Bolivia, 1945, 1946, undated (Box 14, Folder 199)
    - Brazil, 1942, 1944, undated (Box 14, Folder 200)
    - Canada, Nevada, Australia, 1942-1945 (Box 14, Folder 201)
    - Cuba, 1943 (Box 14, Folder 202)
    - Europe, 1943, undated (Box 14, Folder 203)
    - Latin America, 1943-1945, undated (Box 14, Folder 204)
  - Foreign Economic Administration: Metal updates, 1943-1945 (Box 15, Folder 205-206)
  - Geophysic charts, 1943, 1958,1961, undated (Box 15, Folder 207-209)
  - Grade books, 1907-1925 (Box 15, Folder 210-211)
  - Grade books, 1925-1927 (Box 16, Folder 212)
  - Intergovernment agreements: Drafts, 1945, undated (Box 16, Folder 213)
  - Metals reserve: Mexico, 1941, 1942, undated (Box 16, Folder 214)
  - Mexico, 1941-1945 (Box 16, Folder 215)
  - Mineral Resources Committee, 1942-1945 (Box 16, Folder 216-220)
  - Mining and Metallurgical Society of America, 1962 (Box 16, Folder 221)
  - NSRB Reports, 1952 (Box 16, Folder 222)
  - New York Society of Queens University, 1961 (Box 17, Folder 223)
  - "Objectives of U.S. Materials Resources Policy…", 1952 (Box 17, Folder 224)
  - Postwar planning: Mineral policy, 1943-1945 (Box 17, Folder 225-226)
  - President's Materials Policy Commission
    - General
      - 1943-1951 June (Box 17, Folder 227-231)
      - 1951 July-1952, undated (Box 18, Folder 232-239)
      - General, Undated (Box 19, Folder 240)
    - Drafts, 1951 (Box 19, Folder 241)
    - Questionnaire, 1951 (Box 19, Folder 242)
  - Reports: Geological, Miscellaneous, 1923-1960 (Box 19, Folder 243-244)
  - "Rhodesian Selection Trust Properties", 1930 (Box 19, Folder 245)
  - Stamford Sand and Stone Company, 1947-1960 (Box 19, Folder 246)
  - Statistics
    - Budget estimates, 1943, 1944, undated (Box 19, Folder 247)
    - Charts, 1944, undated (Box 19, Folder 248)
    - Imports and exports, 1941-1945, undated (Box 19, Folder 249-251)
    - Production costs, 1943, 1944, undated (Box 20, Folder 252)
  - Stockpiles
    - Army and Navy Munitions Board, 1944, 1945, undated (Box 20, Folder 253)
    - Government, 1943-1945, undated (Box 20, Folder 254)
    - Policy, bills (Box 20, Folder 255)
  - "Taxation of Mineral-Producing Enterprises,", 1949 (Box 20, Folder 256)
  - Technical Industrial Disarmament Committee, 1945 (Box 20, Folder 257)
  - Tremolite Asbestos, 1947 (Box 20, Folder 258)
  - Wilderness Bill, 1961, 1962 (Box 20, Folder 259)
  - Miscellaneous notes on metals and foreign projects, Undated (Box 20, Folder 260)
  - OVERSIZE: Bikita Investigation, Foreign report, 1953 (Box 21, Folder 261)